Guide to the John T. Ridge Collection AIA.068
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
John T. Ridge Collection
1854-1981
AIA.068
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
3.25 linear feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, 3 media boxes, and 3 oversize folders
John T. Ridge is a founding member and current president of the New York Irish History Roundtable. The son of Irish immigrants, Ridge is a Brooklyn-based historian whose work focuses on the influence of social events and organizations such as the Ancient Order of Hibernians, St. Patrick’s Day parades, and Gaelic language clubs, with particular emphasis on the greater New York City area. Materials in this collection include booklets, buttons, ribbons, postcards, broadsides, photographs, advertisements, correspondence, event programs, sheet music, and newspaper and magazine clippings related to Irish and Irish American history in the late 19th- and early 20th-centuries. The majority of the collection documents fraternal and social Irish American organizations in the New York area, as well as numerous nationalist and republican organizations or initiatives.
Ridge, John T.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
John T. Ridge is a founding member and current president of the New York Irish History Roundtable. The son of Irish immigrants, Ridge is a Brooklyn-based historian whose work focuses on the influence of social events and organizations such as the Ancient Order of Hibernians, St. Patrick’s Day parades, and Gaelic language clubs, with particular emphasis on the greater New York City area. He has also led guided tours of immigration facilities and area cemeteries, and given lectures on various aspects of Irish and Irish American history. In addition to numerous essays and journal articles, Ridge also wrote the books The Flatbush Irish, Celebrating 250 Years of the New York City St. Patrick’s Day Parade, Erin’s Sons in America: The Ancient Order of Hibernians, and Sligo in New York: The Irish From County Sligo, 1849-1991.
Related Archival Materials
Collection on the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AIA 046)
Irish Republicanism Collection (AIA 022)
Scope and Content Note
This is an intentionally assembled collection of materials related to Irish and Irish American history in the late 19th- and early 20th-centuries. Materials include booklets, buttons, ribbons, postcards, broadsides, photographs, advertisements, correspondence, event programs, sheet music, and newspaper and magazine clippings. The collection documents various fraternal and social Irish American organizations, with particular emphasis on the Ancient Order of Hibernians divisions located in the greater New York City area, including photographs, convention proceedings, and ledger books. Other materials document American expressions of Irish nationalism and republicanism, including those of the American Commission on Irish Independence, the American League for an Undivided Ireland, the Friends of Irish Freedom, Irish Northern Aid, and the Loyal National Repeal Association. Of note is an issue of John Mitchel's radical nationalist New York newspaper, The Citizen. While the majority of the collection is political in scope, some folders contain advertisements, documents, or photographs of Irish actors, commercial goods, or theatrical performances.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Ridge, 2012.
Ancient Order of Hibernians.; Ireland |x History |y 20th century; Ireland |x Politics and government |y 20th century.; Irish Americans |x Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans |x Social life and customs.; Irish Americans |x Societies, etc.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs.
- "The 69th (Irish) Regiment Emarking In the "James Adger" For the War, April 23, 1961," Harper's, May 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Advertisement: Irish Beauty, Shamrock Oranges, circa 1937 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Advertisement: McQuade's Mountain Dew Whisky, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Advertisement: Schultz's Irish Soap, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- American Commission on Irish Independence, May 21, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American League for an Undivided Ireland, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: Annual Luncheon, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: Division 9 Finance Books (9th Ward/Crown Heights, Brooklyn), 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: Division 35 (Flatbush, Brooklyn) Group Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: Kings County Convention By-laws, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 53rd National Convention Proceedings, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 62nd National Convention Proceedings, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 66th National Convention Proceedings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 67th National Convention Official Call, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 69th National Convention Proceedings, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 74th National Convention, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: Passwords and Quiz, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: Ribbons, Badges, and Buttons, 1890-1975 (Box 3-4)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Objects are extremely fragile and cannot be removed from their housing without approval and assistance from Conservation department.
- Ancient Order of Hibernians: Ritual Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
- Artwork: Robert Emmet, "Ireland's Illustrious Sons," Ancient Order of Hibernians Ladies Auxiliary, undated (Flat-file 7, Drawer H, Folder 3)
- Cassidy, Charles W., 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Barry and Fay's Comedy Co.: "Muldoon's Picnic", Dec 19, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Broadsides, John Devoy, Longstrike and Scenes in the Life of Robert Emmet, Shaughran, 1867, 1874, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Catholic Temperance Abstinence Union of America, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Cigar Labels, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- The Citizen [John Mitchel], 1854 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Comhaltas Ceoltoiri Eireann: Annual U.S. Concert Tour of All-Ireland Champions, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Corcoran, Col. Michael, circa 1863 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- County Cavan Society, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- County Tyrone Society, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "The Escape of Stevens" Broadside, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Fate of the Irish Republic," The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator, circa 1878-1951 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Fenian Bond, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Friends of Irish Freendom: General, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
- Friends of Irish Freedom: Constitution, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Friends of Irish Freedom: "The Escape from Mountjoy and Other Prison Experiences of an irish Volunteer, Padraic Fleming", circa 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Friends of Irish Freedom: Financial Secretary's Files, 1920 (Box 5)
- Friends of Irish Freedom: Membership Applications, 1920 (Box 5)
- Friends of Irish Freedom: Membership Renewals and New Membership Cards, 1920 (Box 5)
- Frontispiece Featuring New York City Mayor John T. Hoffman, after 1866 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "In Memory of Charles O'Connor", Dec 8, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Irish American Democratic Union, circa 1890-1895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Irish Northern Aid (Brooklyn), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Irish Race Fund, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator, 1911 (Flat-file 7, Drawer H, Folder 1)
- The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator, Jun 3, 1911 (Flat-file 7, Drawer H, Folder 2)
- Letters to John From Ed, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Loyal National Repeal Association, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Loyal Orange Lodge, Dec 10, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Memorial Card: Seaun Allis Treacy, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Millard, Dr. S.L. (Boston), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Joseph Murphy's Three Great Irish Plays, late 1800s (Box 2, Folder 13)
- New York County Service Bounty, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "O'Donovan Rossa's Shooting Gallery," Puck, Jan 21, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Olcott, Chauncey, circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- O'Mahony, John, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Postcards, undated (Box 5)
- Second Boer War, circa 1899-1902 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Sheet Music: "Aileen Mavourneen", circa 1860 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Sheet Music: "The Bells of St. Patrick's Cathedral", after 1951 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Sheet Music: "The Irishman's Shanty", after 1859 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Sheet Music: "Since Home Rule's Come to Ireland", 1914 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- St. Patrick's Cathedral, 1862-1866 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- St. Patrick's Cathedral Cornerstone Laying, The Emerald, 1868 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Stephens, James [ Harper's], Jun 2, 1866 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- "Sweet Dreams" Cartoon in Judge, circa 1881-1947 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Tailteann Games, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Theater Programs: "The Little Irish Girl," "The Voice of McConnell", circa 1918-1926 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- United Irish Counties Association (UICA) Feis Card, Jun 13, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- United Irishmen Philadelphia Records, 1792-1799 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- "Wearing of the Green," Arrah Na Pogue, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 11)